This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Hello SE Radio listeners. I'm Po Chan,
head of engineering at ClickSend. We're
a cloud communications company. If
you're considering building text
messaging into your projects, you'll
like using our SMS API. Tens of
thousands of engineers around the world
do.
Plus, for SE Radio listeners, there's
$50 of free credit to try ClickSend.
Just visit clicksend.com/seradio.
Now, enjoy the podcast.
Hi all, welcome to this episode of
Software Engineering Radio. Our guest
today is Nikel Shetty.
Nikel is an expert in networking and
distributed systems. He has worked at
Juniper Networks, Cisco Systems, and
Oracle Cloud Infrastructure.
For Oracle Cloud Infrastructure, Nikel
has helped design and develop the
monitoring and automation platforms that
manage OCI's global network. He's
currently helping develop service for
OCI's AI supercluster networks.
His interests include network
observability, data pipelines, and
control planes. I like to point out that
Nikel and I both work for Oracle.
Nikel was introduced to me and he came
highly recommended by someone
in my network when I was looking for a
guest to speak about this topic on VPC.
Nikel, welcome to the show. It's great
to have you here. Is there anything else
you'd like to add to your bio before we
get started?
Thanks for having me here, Kanchan. This
is a great opportunity for me and I'd
like to really thank you for inviting me
into this podcast.
Nothing else to add. You've given a
great introduction of yourself. Thank
you.
Great. So, let's just start with
describing the big picture for some
time.
And the very first question would be
what is a virtual private cloud?
And then we will go on to discuss why is
it fundamental to building on the cloud,
what is the underlying technology, and
some issues and monitoring aspects. But,
can you describe what is a virtual
private cloud?
Yep. So, I think before we start here, I
think one of the things in, you know,
these fields in networking and other
fields is that experts tend to use
acronyms, right? So, you'll use terms
like VPC, VPN, and things like that. So,
you'll hear a lot of acronyms. What you
want to do is over my experience over
all the years has been, you know,
digging deeper into that acronym, see
what it what each of those terms like
stand for. So, in this particular case,
VPC stands for virtual private cloud as
you clearly mentioned.
If you dig into it, the first term would
be virtual. So, obviously it's virtual
rather than physical, right? So, that
itself kind of gives you some hint about
what this is. The next term is private,
right? So, private is it's not public,
right? It's the opposite of public. So,
it's something that you kind of gives
you another hint about what this thing
is. And finally, cloud, right? Cloud is
something that's running not on your
laptop or desktop, but it's running
somewhere else and you're connecting to
it over the network, right? So, now if
you put all of these together, a virtual
private cloud would be a cloud that is
not physically yours, right? So, it's
virtually yours. It's private, that
means it's not public, which means, you
know, others cannot see your traffic,
you know, they there might be other
customers who who cannot actually access
the traffic that you're sending on this
particular cloud.
And then of course, it's a cloud, so
it's not on your laptop or desktop. It's
somewhere sitting connected to to the
network basically, right? So, a bunch of
software and services. And you have a
network, most likely the internet, over
which you're going to access this these
services. So, essentially that's what a
virtual private cloud would be. Where it
becomes interesting is
what is the relationship with a public
cloud, right? So, what's a public cloud?
So, by definition a public cloud would
be one of the big uh hyperscalers like
AWS, GCP, OCI, things like that. These
are all public clouds. The reason they
are public is because, you know, they
are publicly accessible, all the
services and softwares publicly
accessible. Some of the services may
also be accessible over the internet,
right?
But, what you when you have a virtual
public virtual private cloud within a
public cloud, what it means is you get
your own chunk of that public cloud in
which you can run your own software and
services. And
you know, it'll be virtual, obviously,
because it's not physically yours.
It'll be private, so others cannot view
it. It's isolated from other customers.
And of course, it's running in the
cloud. So, that's what I would call a
VPC.
However, there's another term called
private cloud,
which I believe is stands for something
quite different. Do you want to clarify?
Yeah, so private cloud in general, it
kind of refers to, you know, your
on-premise networks. So, traditionally
all your software and services they've
been delivered through
uh private data centers. Like, so you so
essentially this is like physically
private data centers that you own. You
own all the servers, you'd own the
networking, you'd own all the storage,
right? And that would be your private
cloud, right? So, that is
you know,
when you say cloud, you usually expect
things like, "Hey, I get on-demand
compute, I get storage on demand, things
like that." So, those things you could
replicate in your own on-premise data
center, right? You could have like, for
example, VMware that manages your
servers, you get VMs on the fly.
You could have some kind of maybe a
NetApp storage grid that kind of gives
you object storage kind of services. So,
you could do all the services that are
running in the cloud in your own private
data center. So, that becomes your
private cloud. These things become
quickly complicated, however, because
you sometimes you don't want to run
everything. You maybe you have a private
cloud, maybe you have a dedicated
infrastructure running on premises, but
you want to connect to some services
that you're actually running on the
public cloud, right? So, you have a VPC
and then you have a dedicated data
center. How do you connect them
together, right? At that point it
becomes like a hybrid cloud. So, that's
another term that you might hear in the
industry, hybrid cloud. So, that means
some of your applications are on
premise,
some of them are running in a VPC in a
public cloud and you're kind of
connecting them together. The other term
that you might hear is multi-cloud,
right? So, what is multi-cloud? So, when
as a company you want to put some of
your applications and services in the
cloud,
you may decide, "Hey, you know what? I
don't want to be attached to one public
cloud. I don't want to be attached to
one vendor." So, it's kind of like a
multi-vendor strategy where I want to
now put my services and applications
across multiple clouds. So, I could, you
know, put something in AWS, put
something in Azure, put something in
GCP, and then I kind of now want these
applications maybe to even talk to each
other, right? So, then it becomes a
multi-cloud kind of infrastructure. So,
that's the term you will keep hearing as
well, multi-cloud.
And, you know, looking further, I think
these boundaries are getting even more
blurred, right? There are things like
AWS Outpost or Azure Stack, right? So,
where you can get a a server rack that's
running in your on-premise
and running AWS services or Azure
services right there, right? And, you
know, what services you're interested
in, if you're interested in only storing
the data locally, you know, those things
could be run in that particular server
rack. And then that server rack could
reach out back to the public cloud for
all the other services that you have,
right? You maybe you have a VPC there.
So, you have other applications
installed there, and this outpost would
kind of reach out for those services
there.
Recently, there is also a new product
that was introduced by OCI, which is
which is called dedicated cloud. So,
it, you know, again, this is dedicated
infrastructure,
but then, you know, kind of managed by
OCI. So, OCI would actually install all
the cloud services in your dedicated
data center. So, it's all dedicated for
you, but it has all the services that
the cloud offers.
And at the same time, you you benefit
from having the data locally for
whatever reason. It could be latency, it
could be security, right? So, all of
these terms getting a little bit blurred
and complicated, but at a high level,
you know, just let's make sure that you
understand what a VPC is. VPC is running
in a public cloud, and then you have all
of these other combinations where, you
know, I have some on-premise stuff,
which is the private cloud. Maybe I have
a mix of both, or maybe I have multiple
of these VPCs in different clouds. So,
all of those have different terms that
you refer to them with.
You know, you've talked in a little bit
detail of the VPC and on premises and
the different combinations there. How do
you connect between the on premises
cloud and the public cloud? Is that the
VPN or virtual private network? Is that
right?
That is correct, yes. So, if you, you
know, if you search for VPN online, I'm
sure you'll find a bunch of free
services and even paid services which
let you uh join a VPN, right? And from
your laptop, you could join a VPN, and,
you know, all your data traffic, all
your internet traffic, all your browsing
goes over that encrypted conne-
connection. It's basically like a tunnel
between your laptop and the VPN server,
right? And then, you know, once it it's
all tunneled, so all your data is
hidden. So, let's say if you're in a
Wi-Fi in a cafe, in a public cafe, like
Starbucks Wi-Fi or something, you don't
want any of your data to be visible,
like what what kind of activities you're
doing. So, you put it in a tunnel,
right?
You want to do the same thing for your
enterprise, right? So, you have an
on-premise data center, and you have a
VPC in the public cloud.
How do you connect them together? You
want to actually encrypt it end-to-end,
put all your data traffic in a tunnel,
so no one can see it. You own all the
keys, right? For all of this encrypted
communication. And that's what a VPN
would be, right? So, that's what a
virtual private network. Usually, the
this is built on top of a technology
called IPsec, right? So, you have an
IPsec VPN that you set up. And as I
said, you could do a VPN from your
laptop, but for these high-fidelity
VPNs, you usually you'd have some kind
of customer premise equipment, which
you'll install in your on-premise data
center, and then that would connect to
the cloud service, which offers like the
endpoint of your VPN. And then, all the
traffic that lands at that endpoint in
the cloud is dropped into your VPC, to
go to its appropriate location within
the VPC.
So, before we get into some more of the
technology that this is built on, I'd
like to point folks to episode 571, Jay
Mulder on multi-cloud governance, that
has covered some of the related topics
here as well. So, Nick, let's spend some
time now on the underlying technology to
some extent. Perhaps, maybe with an
example. So, if somebody has a
three-tier web app, if you can keep that
in mind and then talk about some of the
concepts
related, starting with the VPC.
What if the VPC is not created at all?
What happens?
Okay. So, if a VPC is not created at
all, and you know, maybe your first
interaction with the cloud is, "Hey, I
want an instance, right? I want a VM to
run something." Most clouds would create
a default VPC for you.
Right?
That takes care of like all your basics
and, you know, any of the communication
between instances in that VPC and things
of that sort. But, in general,
the default VPC may not work for you
because it'll have some simplistic
settings. For instance, like you'll have
full access to the internet.
Right?
And we just talked about the private
network. Maybe you don't want your
instances to be on the internet because
that's, you know, you're exposing
yourself to security hacks and things of
that sort, right? Like, so if you look
at like the Swiss cheese model of
security, avoiding instances from being
on the internet is kind of like one
layer of your Swiss cheese model of
security, right? So, it won't be
sufficient, but it's kind of like maybe
a necessary thing. You want to keep them
away. So, what you want to watch out
for, you can always, you know, use
services on on the public cloud, create
your own tenancy, you know, start using
maybe some instances,
maybe you want to bring up some
containers, right? Things like that.
But, they may all land up in the default
VPC, which is not what you want because
some of the settings of the default VPC
may not be to your liking. Right? So,
going back to your question, what you
would want to do is you want to create
one VPC. So, in this case, let's say
let's take a naive three-tier web app,
right? Let's say I take create a VPC and
I will use a term called cider, which
we'll try to explain in a bit. So, let's
say you create a VPC, it has a cider of
10.0.0.0/16,
and then I create three tiers, right?
So, the web tier, the app tier, and the
DB tier.
So, the web tier, I could put it in the
subnet. Let's say I call Let's say I
take that's a subnet of this cider,
which is
Let's say 10.0.1.0/24.
Okay? And then I could do another subnet
for the app tier, which would be
10.0.2.0/24.
And then for the DB tier, it'd be
10.0.3.0/24.
Right? So, I I can kind of break up my
VPC this way into multiple subnets, put
my different tiers in those subnets. And
then, you know, for each of those
subnets, I can have different kind of
settings, right? So, for instance,
the web tier, I want access to the
public internet. So, I need to do do
something for that, right? And we'll
come We'll come to all of this about
internet gateway and stuff like that
later. The app tier only needs to talk
to the web tier and the DB tier, right?
So, you will set up the subnet rules
appropriately. Finally, the DB tier only
needs to talk to the app tier, right?
So, how do you set up something like
that? So, you will see that as part of
all the as as we discuss more of the
concepts here, you'll see how you how
you kind of achieve that, basically.
You talked about subnets, and then I
think you mentioned splitting the IP
address space across the subnets.
What is the address space? You know, is
that the private address space? And can
you please describe that a little bit,
and then maybe talk about cider blocks,
as well?
I introduced the term cider, and again,
cider here stands for CIDR, right? So,
for folks on the audio who may not know
this terminology.
And again, back to what I said, let's
expand the acronym and let's work on it.
So, it's stands for classless
inter-domain routing, which sounds
pretty complicated, right? So, what do
you mean by classless, right? So,
when the internet started out, you have
these IPv4 addresses, which are, you
know, 32-bit addresses
or 4 bytes, basically, right?
So, when the internet started out, they
initially had the sense that, "Hey, I
would break these into multiple classes
of addresses, right? Some addresses
would have the first 24 bits fixed. And
now you can play around with the last
eight bits, right? So, you get 2 to the
power eight different addresses, which
is 256 addresses.
Right? So, some customers on the
internet would be happy with that class
C address space.
Then there would be some who would be
happy with the class B address space,
which is take the first two bytes /16.
And then that's 16 bits, right? So, you
can now modify the remaining 16 bits, so
that's 2 to the power 16, which is
65,000 addresses. And then maybe there
are some who are really big. For them,
you know, you keep the first eight bits
fixed, and the remaining 24 bits, which
is 2 to the power 24, so 16 million
addresses.
Immediately, you know, people realized,
"Hey, that is too rigid of a system,
right? Because what if I needed only
10,000 addresses? I can't use a class C
space. I'd have to use multiple class C
spaces.
Or I have to then buy a class B space,
which is 65K, which might be too
expensive for me." So, you want now all
different kinds of
intermediate breakup of this address
space, right? So, they completely let go
this class-based addressing.
And they said, "Hey, let's just do it
classless, right? So, I just say that,
'Hey, this is my prefix, and these are
the bits of the prefix that are
significant, and everything under that
is owned by this particular, let's say,
autonomous system. That's the
terminology that's used.
So, you'll see the way we are using
CIDRs in VPC is just a way to notate,
annotate, and address, basically, right?
So, you'll say
I have 10.0.0.0/
let's say 18. That's my CIDR, right? So,
what that means is
10.0.0 is the address. If you take the
prefix, first 18 bits of it, that's what
would be fixed,
right? And everything else, the
remaining 14 bits, so I get 2 to the 14
addresses, which I can use in my VPC in
any way I choose. I can break it into
multiple subnets, whatever I want to do
with it.
So, that's where the CIDR terminology
comes from. You could just probably call
it a prefix and be done with it. You
don't have to call it CIDR, right? But,
that's the terminology that's been used,
so we need to just understand it.
Same thing applies to IPv6. The only
difference is that's 128 bits of address
space, right? You can, again, break it
down in any sequence, any prefix that
you want.
You know, coming back to the question of
what is a private address space?
So, the IETF, basically, it set aside
some addresses for folks to use within
their organizations,
right? So, these are private spaces,
which are not publicly routable over the
internet, right? So, if you take an
address in the space, you try to send
some packet, you know, over the
internet, you cannot go,
right? You maybe you can only go within
your private network, private corporate
network, or something like that.
So, accordingly, what IETF IETF did was
they set aside these address spaces. One
of those was 10.0.0/8.
That means the first 10 is fixed, and
then you have three bytes or 2 to the
power 24 addresses, which you can use
any way you want. Right? So, 10/8 The
other space is 172.16/12.
Another one is 192.168/16.
And as I told you, like the longer the
prefix, the lesser the number of
addresses that you have.
Right? So, I mean, if you're setting up
a VPC, you probably just want to take
the biggest one because you don't know
how much you're going to grow, how
successful you're going to be. So, you
just take 10 Let's say 10.0.0
/16, and that's your CIDR block that you
assign to your VPC. So, question you
could ask me is, you know, why can't I
use a public address space? Right? And
the answer to that is absolutely you
could use a public address space in your
VPC, but imagine what would happen.
Right? Let's walk through that scenario.
So, as an example, I know that 8.8.8.8
is a very well-known address, which is
on the internet. This is Google's DNS
service, basically.
So, now imagine you had a VPC, right,
which was 8.8.0.0/16.
And then in that VPC, you created a
subnet called 8.8.8/24.
And now you attach an instance in that
subnet.
What if it got the address 8.8.8.8?
What would you do then? Right? If your
instance really wanted to access
Google's DNS service for whatever
reason,
all the packets would just come to this
instance rather than going over the
internet to the Google's DNS service.
Right? So, the answer to that is you can
use your public address space, but you
have to be so confident that, you know,
you're never going to use or never going
to access any public service that exists
in that address space.
So, usually the recommendation is, you
know, don't do that. Like, just use one
of the private address spaces, and if
you're really running out of them, then
maybe you think about, you know, pulling
up some of the public spaces and adding
it to your VPC, right?
Definitely not recommended, but, you
know, if you know what you're doing,
maybe you can go ahead and do it.
So, you talked about using the prefix
16.
Why would I not just reserve the largest
space?
Yeah, so those would be restrictions
from your cloud. So, if your cloud
provider allows you to create CIDR
blocks with
/12, but you can do 10.0.0/12.
Right? You don't have to do 10.
And what is the reasons for the provider
to restrict it?
It would be some kind of internal
restriction, like their stack maybe just
doesn't support it, right? Maybe the way
they've designed their internal software
to handle all of this. It just doesn't
support that kind of ranges.
So, you will see, you know, those kind
of differences between the clouds. Maybe
some of them have designed it that way
to provide that flexibility, some have
not, right?
So, you'll see different kind of ranges
that are kind of supported.
And I think you hinted at this, but can
you just explicitly state the difference
between what I understand are public
subnets and private subnets?
Okay. So, I started out by saying that
we have a three-tier app, right? The web
tier, the app tier, and the DB tier, and
each of those is in its own subnet,
right?
And we said that the web tier
would need access to the internet. So,
it's it's probably a great time here to
talk about what are route tables, right?
So, route tables are something that
allow the routing to happen
in a subnet. So, what it tells you is,
"Hey, for this particular destination,
how do you want to get to it? Like, you
know, which subnet should I go to?
Right? Or do I need to go to something
else, like some other device, like a
gateway, right? To reach a certain
target." So, what you do is you give a
prefix or a cider
and you say, "Hey, this destination,
this is the target I want to do." Right?
And the route tables usually work on
longest prefix match. Right? So, if you
have a longer prefix in the route table,
that is what will get matched rather
than the shorter one. Right? So,
essentially, each of these subnets, they
have a route table. The default route
table usually will have all the subnet
related prefixes in them. Right? And
will tell, "Okay, for this prefix, go to
this subnet." Basically, right? So, that
that kind of mapping would already be
there.
But, sometimes you want to add
additional entries like, "Hey, I want to
go to 8.8.8.8."
Right? So, take the internet gateway
when I want to do that. Right? So,
that's the route that you will add.
So, now I've been talking about internet
gateway. Right? So, that it's a network
function, essentially, which allows you
to reach out to the internet. Okay? So,
when a subnet has a route table entry
that allows it to go to the internet
over an internet gateway,
that's when you say that the subnet is
public in nature.
Okay? So, with that, what happens is any
instance
that is in that subnet, if it can now
start talking to internet addresses and
it may be assigned an address over the
internet. Right? Not a private address.
Everything already has a private
address.
It'll get a public address, maybe
dynamically or it could be an elastic
address. That's a separate discussion.
It'll get a public address over for the
internet and all traffic will now go
through the internet gateway and can
reach to the internet, basically.
Uh so, that's what a public subnet is.
Right? So, as I said, you have the route
table
and you have the internet gateway. Once
you do that, you get an address on the
public internet and you can talk to the
internet from that instance.
The interesting thing here is there is
something called a NAT gateway as well
where
your private
instances, your private subnets, can
also access the internet. Right? So,
again, we're blurring the boundaries
here, but just to be clear, the private
subnet can also access the internet via
the NAT gateway.
What it cannot do is allow communication
from outside in the internet
into that subnet. Right? So, it'll allow
one-sided communication. So, it'll, you
know, the instance can open up a
connection out to 8.8.8 for instance if
you wanted access to the Google DNS.
Right?
But, Google's DNS cannot open a
connection to that instance. Right? So,
that would be completely impossible.
So, you have internet gateway and the
NAT gateway and then, you know, use
internet gateway when you want both-side
connections to be allowed, right? From
the instance or from the internet.
And you use the NAT gateway if you want
to keep this subnet as private, but
still want some kind of access to the
internet. And that's where the route
tables also come into play because now
you can specifically say, "Hey, you know
what? I want this instance to only
access 8.8.8." So, maybe in the route
table I only add that entry and nothing
else. Right? So, anything else I try to
reach out over the internet,
it's going to be denied, basically.
So, that's kind of, you know, you can
think of it like another layer of your
Swiss cheese model of security,
basically. Right? So, this is another
layer.
Okay. So, I think that kind of covers
both of these.
And, you know, back to what you asked me
about subnets, public and private. So,
in our case, in our example,
what I would do is I would create an
internet gateway, attach it in the VPC.
I would add a route table entry for the
web tier subnet
to say, let's say let's say default for
now, right? So, anything for the
internet just go to the internet
gateway.
Maybe I need 8.8.8, so I will say create
a NAT gateway, attach it to the VPC. Now
my app tier and my DB tier, I say
anything that wants to go to 8.8.8
add a route table entry, target would be
the NAT gateway. Right? So, now those
instances have access to 8.8.8.
And that would kind of set up all my
communications for me, basically.
So, continuing on the security model,
I've heard of security groups and
network ACLs.
Mhm.
Can you help us understand what they are
and when should one be used versus the
other?
So, we already talked about security in
one sense, which is in terms of like
access. How do I restrict access to the
internet, for instance, right? How do I
keep my instances private, right?
One other way to do security is to kind
of enforce all kinds of communication
that an instance can do. Okay?
And here I think it you know, I've been
using the term instance and a subnet,
right?
The more accurate relationship is
actually a network interface on an
instance and subnet. Okay, so I just
wanted to bring up that
distinction here.
An instance could have multiple network
interfaces, right? And they could be in
different subnets.
Okay? So, really when I say instance
till now in this whole talk, I was
referring to a network interface of an
instance. Okay?
So, now a security group, what's a
security group? Security group is like
an allowed communication for a certain
instance.
And you can say, "Hey, what's the
protocol? What's the port range? You
know, whether it's an ICMP traffic or
not? What are the source and
destinations that you allow the
communication from and to, right?
So, you can provide these as a rule and
attach it to an instance class, right?
So,
that's what a network security group is
and that would automatically any
instance that you spawn in that instance
class on all the network interfaces of
that instance, you would apply this
network security group. Okay? So, this
is point out network security group
associated with an instance, it applies
to all interfaces on that instance.
Then there is something called as ACLs,
which can be set up in a subnet, right?
So, those are associated with the subnet
rather than the instance.
And then ACLs are very similar, they
have the same kind of match criteria,
right? You have like the protocol, port,
source, destination, things like that.
The difference would be that ACLs would
tell you what is allowed or denied,
right? So, each entry can actually be
specific to allow or deny, while network
security groups, they're just saying,
"Okay, these communications are
allowed." And by default, everything
else is denied, right?
So, ACLs kind of support this more
granular kind of allow and deny rules,
basically.
And back to what I said, the network
security group goes with the instance.
The network ACLs operates at the subnet
level. So, that's the distinction. You
can always have a security group for a
certain instance class
and then the network ACL could also
replicate the same thing. It just adds
another layer, basically, right? So, in
case you messed up something on the
security group, at least the network ACL
kind of protects you. Or vice versa,
like you messed up something on the
network ACL, the network security group
kind of helps you. So, both of them have
a place in your security architecture.
Usually, what would be recommended by
most cloud operators is to use NSGs
because they go with your instances. You
don't have to worry about which subnet
you're putting this instance in.
Right? So, for example, let's say your
app tier. I started with an example just
with one instance, but maybe in the
future I have
thousands of instances and I exhausted
my subnet. I need to create one more
subnet.
Now, when I create the subnet,
if the network security group that goes
with this instance class,
if the instance class remains the same,
the network security group continues to
apply. Right? So, even if I change the
subnet,
the NSG would still continue to apply,
but the network ACL I would have to
explicitly put on that new subnet as
well.
Right? So, that's the benefit. So,
you're kind of decoupling the security
of an instance class from what your
network structure is for that particular
instances.
So, for network ACLs you mentioned
there's both allow and deny rules.
That's a little confusing to me. So,
what happens to what is not either
specified as allowed or denied?
So, usually these rules have to specify
whether the certain flow is allowed or
not. Right? And then whether it is deny
or not. Right? So,
what you could have is for example, you
could have a network security group that
says, "Hey, give me all SSH
connections." Right? So, that could be
very simple network security group. Port
22.
Protocol is TCP. Allow everything.
Right? And then the network ACL could
say, "You know what? Actually, do not
allow traffic coming from certain range
because I know that's not a good range
or it's coming from my competitor." Or
something like that. Or you know that
there are bad actors on that range of
addresses. So, you can specifically go
and say, "Hey, deny anything that comes
from that particular range." Right? So,
that kind of helps you with the denying
of access essentially.
One other thing that we should also keep
in mind is the network security group.
Every rule in the network security group
is evaluated.
But on the ACLs, the way the ACLs work
is the first match that you get to an
ACL, that's the ACL that will be used.
So, if you have a deny at the top
somewhere and that gets matched, then
your traffic will be denied.
Right, it will not go and see, okay, is
anything anything else allowing this
traffic? So, it goes in sequence and
evaluates all the rules one by one. So,
all of this by the way, network ACLs,
you know, come more from the networking
side where, you know, network devices
used to have these ACLs in order and
things like that. Whereas the security
groups, they come more from the
application side. So, that's the way
kind of think about it. And both have
their place basically and both have
their utilities.
So, we've talked about VPCs and subnets
in some detail.
I'm wondering, are there scenarios where
you would have multiple VPCs?
Multiple VPCs, yes, it's possible you
can have multiple VPCs. One way you can
think of adding multiple VPCs is, so,
remember what I said, this I have a
three-tier web app, right?
Maybe I have another web app, which is
another three tiers and I want to manage
it separately. Right, so I put it in a
separate VPC
and manage all of its interconnectivity
that way, right?
I could have organizational boundaries.
Right, so I could say that maybe the
sales team has whole VPC and they have a
bunch of services there.
And then there is a engineering team
which has a completely different VPC
with their own subnets, right? Or maybe
even within that, there is a VPC for
development stuff, right? So, it kind of
provides that isolation, right? So, you
make any changes, you don't impact some
other application. Right, so that's one
benefit.
The other benefit is you can drive kind
of management of these VPCs through
separate odds basically. Right, so I
think that's another benefit of having
multiple VPCs.
I mean, in general if you're a small
application developer, probably you
don't need multiple VPCs. But, you know,
as you grow
and your you know, your organization
becomes complex,
the services and applications that you
provide become complex, you may want to
kind of isolate your applications from
each other.
I'm interested in scenarios that require
connecting instances in two different or
two or more different VPCs. Let's talk
to
How does that work? And you know, I've
heard of issues with that with cider
overlaps. Could you cover that?
Yeah.
So, what does cider overlap mean? Right,
so let's take this example. I said
10.0.0.0/16
is a cider in my VPC. Now, if I create
another VPC and I use the exact same
cider block,
there is a potential that when I try to
connect them together, and the way to
connect them together is something
called VPC peering.
Right? So, I could peer these VPCs
together so that, you know, all the
subnets in each of these VPCs now can
see each other. Right? But, the minute
you do that, if there is the same
address being used in another subnet in
another VPC in the other VPC,
it will cause an overlap. Right, so
you cannot do that
unless there is some kind of NAT
translation that you can do.
And you know, NAT stands for network
address translation. Right?
So, as you go between the VPCs, if you
can
transform your IP address into something
that only the other VPC understands,
right? Then you could do that
communication, but it's pretty complex
and these are all new kind of features
that are there in the public clouds
because of some of these things that
they observed with overlaps and stuff
like that. But the best way to avoid
this kind of overlap is you just avoid
them right in the first place, which is,
you know, get different address spaces,
right? Like if you know you're one big
organization, try to keep them separate,
right? So, you want to do some kind of
IP address management. And there are a
lot of tools that these public cloud
vendors would provide you like how to
manage your IP address space,
how to monitor how much of it is used,
things of that sort. So, definitely you
should investigate and look into those
features. So, as to avoid these kind of
overlaps because getting into the
overlaps, I think it's just going to be
very complicated to resolve eventually.
So, better planning, I would say, is the
way to go about it. The more complicated
use cases, I have a dedicated private
cloud, right? On premise. Now, if I'm
connecting that to the VPC that I have
in the public cloud, or I have multiple
VPCs in multiple public clouds and I
want to now start talking between them.
So, you really want an organization-wide
view of all the address space that
you're using. So, yeah. You definitely
need to plan for it. I think planning is
super important here.
It's interesting.
Like I know from just scenarios I've
seen recently,
it's very hard to envision what might
happen. So, suddenly understanding what
are the options and doing the
translation.
So, as I said, there is this option of a
NAT gateway that you could put a private
NAT gateway, right? This is not the NAT
gateway that goes to the internet, but
between your VPCs, you could have like
NAT gateway that translates your
addresses into something that the other
end understands and does not overlap
with something that the other end has,
right? But, you know, that just reduces
the amount of option you have in terms
of communication. As I said, you know,
NAT, you can only initiate a connection
in one direction, right?
So, maybe that works for a lot of the
applications, but if you wanted to now
do the communication both directions,
what would you do? Now, you want to then
move it make two gate- not gateways, one
in each direction. I don't know. Like,
so it starts getting complicated very
quickly. Yeah.
So, there was a term called private link
when connecting VPCs that I came across.
I'm not sure if you talked about that
already. I don't think explicitly, but I
don't know if you talked about it.
I I didn't speak about it. It's kind of
related to the VPC peering in a way,
where, you know, if you have a service
that's maybe hosted by another AWS
account, right?
So, instead of doing VPC peering with
that other service, right? By the way,
it need not be a
completely different AWS account. It
could be an AWS service, but you want
that service to be kind of visible
within your subnet
in a private address space. You don't
want to go public, right?
How would you do that is via something
called private endpoint, right? So, what
that would do is So, take an example of
this database, right?
Maybe AWS, maybe the public cloud has a
database service
that allows you to have a private
endpoint in your subnet,
which you can access it via, right? So,
now in your subnet, you can say, "Hey, I
want to add this private endpoint of
this database service." So, the database
service will show up like as if it's a
network interface or an instance in that
private subnet,
though it's really a service, you know,
backed by a proper cloud service, right?
I think on the other end. so but it look
like an instance to you, right? So, you
can talk to it like an instance. You
don't you know, it's within your subnet,
so you don't maybe you don't even need
special protections and things like
that. Your traffic does not exit the VPC
and maybe, you know, go into some kind
of public arena, right? So, all of those
benefits exist.
So, you could do that. You could attach
the database service into your database
subnet and then maybe you have just a
small thing there which allows you to
access that endpoint, basically, right?
So, and you can call all the APIs of
that service just like as if it's a
service that you delivered, right? You
built and you put it in your subnet. So,
it look like that.
So, that's something that private
endpoint and you know, you can use this
for attaching other AWS accounts as
well, right?
As long as they have support for private
links, they can provide this service to
you. You can again add those services as
a private endpoint in your subnet and
then access those services via that
private endpoint.
So, yeah, I think that kind of hopefully
covers it and answers your question
around it.
Yeah, thanks, Nick. So,
here in the last several minutes we've
been talking about some other key
technology that people would use. Now,
I'd like to drill into very specific
topics. We can pick a couple and drill
into that. The first one was bring your
own IP. Where does that fit and why
would one do that?
Yeah. So, there are a lot of these
organizations, big organizations that
are kind of migrating to the cloud,
right? So, previously they had maybe an
on-premise infrastructure.
Maybe they bought a bunch of public
addresses. So, by the way, public IPv4
space is extremely scarce and expensive.
So, maybe you already bought it, right?
And you've been using some of these
public address spaces.
Maybe you're even giving it to some of
your customers and said, "Hey,
can you please whitelist my public
address space, right, for some service
or something, right?"
When you go to the cloud and you are
saying, "Hey, give me a public IP
address, right?" You get a public IP
address from the cloud's address space.
But maybe that's not what you want.
Maybe you want to continue to offer your
services from your address space. So,
you leverage anything all your customers
have kind of set up
a whitelist for your address space
somehow.
So, you want to leverage that. You want
to continue to leverage that instead of
asking them, "Hey, you know what? Now
I'm going to get this dynamic address
from my cloud provider." Maybe I have
multiple cloud providers. That becomes
even more complex.
So, instead of that, you what you do is
you take your IP space, bring it to the
cloud, and give it to the cloud operator
and say, "Hey,
I have this public IP space.
When my instance is trying to talk out
to the internet, please assign an
address from this space instead, right?"
So, what does the cloud operator have to
do at that point? There is some work to
be done because they have to verify that
you actually own that address space. Or,
you know, you cannot just take someone
else's address space and say, "Hey,
cloud operator, let's take this as my IP
address space." Right? So, they have to
go and verify that.
So, they would have to verify it with
the regional internet registries or
something.
And then they would accept that space.
And once it's accepted, they would start
advertising
that address space. The cloud operator
would advertise its address space in the
internet,
right, and start attracting traffic for
that address space. And then, you know,
at that point you can start using it,
start assigning instances, applications,
services, whatever you're building on
your on the cloud.
You'll get the same address space
essentially. So, that's what bring your
own IP is.
Another topic that I'm curious about is
monitoring, analytics, and logging. The
IP traffic.
Why is that important? Have you
discovered any interesting patterns
when people do this?
Yeah, good question. So, there are a
bunch of different tools that you can
use when you're debugging, you know, any
connectivity issues in the cloud. Right?
So, you have a VPC,
you could set up flow logging, right?
So, for a subnet.
So, what flow logs will do is it will
tell you, "Hey, what's the flow that's
coming into the subnet? Right? And what
was the action taken by the cloud for
that particular flow? Was it like a deny
or accept? Whatever it is, right?"
That helps because, as I told you, the
security groups and ACLs, they become
quite complicated very quickly, right?
And they may even like override each
other or something, right? So, if you
by mistake had a bad setting on your
ACLs or something which is denying the
traffic that's trying to come into the
subnet,
you will not see anything on your
instance, basically, right? So, at that
point you want to enable flow logs and
say, "Hey, let's see what's happening to
this flow.
Let's see if it's even hitting the
subnet in the first place,
right? Maybe it's not even reaching
subnet. Maybe there's an issue somewhere
else, right?
But at least when it hits the subnet,
you know that
was it accepted? Was it denied? And why
was it denied? Maybe there was a ACL
rule or maybe there was a security group
that kind of denied that access,
basically.
So, that kind of level of debugging
would be enabled if you do flow logs,
right?
The only thing to watch out is with flow
logs, if you have a lot of flows, like
you have a really popular application,
right? That can quickly overwhelm some
of these things. So, you'll have to, you
know, most of these services are
horizontally scalable, but maybe there
are limits and you have to pay more
money in terms of costs for the logs
that you're exporting, right?
So, that's the only thing to kind of
watch out for. There are other tools.
I know there are tools like traffic
mirroring, so you can actually mirror
the complete traffic that an instance is
receiving.
You know, maybe this is useful for some
kind of compliance kind of use cases
that you see in some of the corporate
networks and stuff like that. So, maybe
it's a similar kind of use case that you
want to apply in the virtual private
cloud.
There are also tools like reachability
analyzers tools. So, where you could set
up something like, "Hey, I want to
always monitor my connectivity between a
certain instance IP and the internet,
let's say, right? Some address on the
internet. I want to make sure that that
connection is always up somehow, right?"
So, anytime you make any configuration
changes in your VPC, right?
The reachability analyzer will run again
to verify that that connectivity is
good. And if they figure out, "Oh, you
know what? You just added an ACL here
that denied that traffic,
then it will kind of throw an alert,
right? So, you know, your operators can
get an alert saying, "Oh, you know,
there was a configuration change. The
reachability is now broken, so you may
want to go and fix your configuration."
And so, you get an immediate feedback
rather than, you know, figuring out
later when there is, you know, when
somebody actually does that
communication and they have a problem
with that communication, then debugging
becomes super difficult, right? You have
to like go ping something, you have to
enable flow log, or look in the flow
logs, things like that. So,
so having some kind of reachability
analyzer that kind of analyzes your
route tables, your security groups, your
ACL rules, right?
End to end, I think that is kind of
valuable.
So, the next topic I'd like to chat with
you about, Nikel, is the DNS management
on the VPC.
Could you maybe just start explaining
what DNS manage would do and how would
you configure that on the VPC?
Yeah, so, you know, back to the theme
on, you know, acronyms and stuff like
that. So, DNS
uh for folks who are not initiated into
this, it stands for Domain Name System,
right? So, this is
uh
the way the, you know, you kind of
resolve host names to IP addresses uh to
perform your communications.
Um
So, in case of VPCs, um usually they
would have some kind of uh
default DNS support for your uh for the
instances that you create in the VPC.
Um
what would happen is, you know, you if
you enable the DNS support, um
all the private IP addresses for the
instances would be assigned some kind of
host names.
Um
Some uh you know, you can also actually
go ahead and maybe create your own
personal private domain, and you can
assign that to the VPC.
Um
when you're creating instances, you
know, those instances will get host
names, and then, you know,
those host names will be mapped to those
private addresses.
Um
also, how does that help you, right?
Like uh so, let's say, you know, taking
our example here, the three-tier web
app,
um let's say I have a domain called
example.com, right?
Uh I could say my app is
appinstance.example.com,
my DB would be dbinstance.example.com.
And that way then, when I put
the thing into my configuration of my
application, right? I I just have to say
dbinstance.example.com,
it kind of decouples it
from the actual IP address that's
assigned to that instance.
Um
So, you know, later, let's say if you
actually copied your DB onto another
instance, you could just move that DNS
uh host name onto that IP address.
And you know, nothing has to change on
the application end, right? So, that's
one way you could use it. Uh the other
way you could use it is like you know,
you just want to check connectivity
between these instances.
Uh
you don't have to remember the IP
address of the instance. You can If you
have a way that you have configured all
these host names in your VPC, you can
use you can use that to actually you
know, perform like a ping check or
something of that sort.
Uh in addition, you know, there's also
public DNS that you could use. Most Most
providers would have some kind of public
DNS support. So, in our example, if you
look at the web
uh the web tier, uh it is supposed to be
on the internet. You probably don't want
to give your IP address to someone else.
Rather, you want to give a host name,
right? You want to give a proper domain
name, right? So, for example, in this
case, if it's example.com,
you'd call it hey, web.example.com
and then you kind of associate associate
it with the
the web instance that you have. Or if
you had a load balancer there,
you can associate it with the IP address
of the load bal- the public IP address
of the load balancer.
Uh
Now, in addition
on the public DNS side, there are a lot
of other features that you could use
from the cloud providers. For For
instance, you could do like a DNS
failover, right? So, you have multiple
of these end points.
You could put one DNS entry pointing to
all of these
or pointing to one of them and then, you
know, perform health checks and
monitoring and make sure if if it's not
healthy, you flip over to the backup,
basically.
Right? So, DNS could do a failover
feature could do that for you.
Uh
public DNS also provides other kinds of
features like
you know, kind of routing your
uh request to the closest cloud region.
Uh
or, you know, maybe you can configure
and say, "Hey, if there is a request
that comes from this geography, maybe
from North America, always send it to
maybe the US East region." If it comes
from Europe, you know, always send it to
a Frankfurt region or something of that
sort.
So, there are a lot of these uh things
that you can play around with,
especially with public DNS. And with
that, you can actually create a proper
end-to-end application that's, you know,
globally available
and has a lot of redundancy.
A couple of follow-up questions, Nikhil.
The first one was just in terms of
certificate management for the host
names.
How is that integrated into uh the
setup?
Yeah, so certificate management, there
could be multiple things that you want
to worry about here, right? So, for
example, maybe what you want to validate
is is a certificate that the host is
actually offering me, is it you know, is
it a valid certificate, right? So, for
example, I want to go to SSA I want to
do SSH uh db.example.com,
right? Is it actually the DB host,
right? So, the way it would work is I
would have a CA certificate. So, let
assume let's say the
uh the public cloud provider is the CA
as well.
Maybe you get those trust roots onto
your host so that when you do an uh when
you do some kind of API call to your DB
server and it returns back uh that
certificate, you can actually validate
locally that it's actually the remote
uh
the host is actually who it says it is,
right? Um
and, you know,
uh most of the cloud providers, they
would have some kind of certificate
management where they you can actually
download these certificates onto your
host
uh Uh, maybe in an automatic fashion,
you know, you can kind of, uh, rotate it
periodically. Right? So, all of those
settings, uh, can be tuned.
Um,
the cloud providers could also provide a
way to send these certificates to your
load balancers. So, for example, in this
case, in the web case, maybe, uh, the
load balancer automatically keeps
getting its certificate renewed
periodically, maybe every 30 days,
whatever it is.
Um, and, you know, uh,
it could be signed by a well-known
uh, providers, which, you know, is, uh,
is something that is trusted by all the
browsers throughout the world. So, if
you're actually, you know, coming in
from a browser to your website,
then, you know, your browser should be
able to trust the certificate that it
sees.
Uh, so, it can be signed by one of those
well-known providers as well. So, those
are some of the services that these
cloud, uh, providers can provide you.
So, what about the situation where
the application is a SaaS,
B2B SaaS, let's take that example, and
the customers, um, let's say they are
Pepsi and Coke, each one their end users
to have a unique URL. So, it's a
multi-tenant application.
Um, how would you then manage the DNS to
provide
multiple host names to the same IP?
Multi-tenancy can be implemented in
multiple ways. You know, you could have
a single endpoint, and then, you know,
somehow your requests kind of identify
which tenancy that you're making the
request for. That's one way you can go
about tenancy, but I think what you're
asking is,
um,
can I have two different,
uh,
DNS, uh, domain names, right, for two
different customers of mine?
Right? So, that's definitely something
that's possible.
Uh,
maybe there are, again, within this,
maybe there are multiple ways you could
implement it, right? Um,
maybe you have two different load
balancers,
uh,
with different IPs, so, all the DNS
mapping, everything is uh everything is
different.
Um, or you could have a single load
balancer, and then uh
the DNS request comes in, and based on
what is the address that the request
sees, right? You can forward it to your
appropriate back end, uh which is
actually serving that particular
customer, right? So, things like that.
So, there there there are many ways you
can kind of skin the cat here.
Um, but you know, those are some of the
ways that you can do it, and you know,
one of the ways as you said, uh how do
you use DNS? So, that's one way to use
the DNS. You could assign your public
host name
to different IP addresses. Uh that's one
way you can do it.
Is there any impacts to network latency
that one should be aware of for, you
know, making sure that you're tracking
for any specific configurations?
Yeah, so most of these cloud services,
they would be horizontally scalable,
elastic services, right? So, you can use
as much as you want, right? That's
usually the hyperscaler mantra, right?
What you want to watch out for is, you
know, there might be some things, for
example, so I've not discussed this
before, but maybe this is a good point
to actually talk about load balancers.
You know, in the three-tier web app that
I talked about, I was always giving any
single instance as an example, but
you'll probably never have just a single
instance,
right? You will have multiple instances.
In fact, you will have multiple
instances divided across availability
zones, right?
And what are availability zones? Avail-
availability zones are just zones which
give you enough redundancy, so you know,
you have a data center,
the other availability zone, the data
center might be kilometers away. So, if
there's let's say there's a wildfire,
and one of your data centers goes down,
you still have your instances in other
data centers in that area, maybe 10 km
away or something like that,
which are still up and running and your
services continue to operate basically,
right? Or you don't have to go to
wildfire, you can, you know, you even
think of like a power cut or something,
a simple thing like that, right? If
there's a power issue, you have
something in the other So, now, once you
have multiple instances in your subnet,
how do you manage high availability?
Right? You cannot expect every consumer
to know about all of these and try to
check which of them is healthy and then,
you know, send traffic to that instance.
So, what you want to do is you want to
put kind of a load balancer which
provides both
the high availability, so the load
balancer itself can verify, you know,
which of these instances is healthy and
send traffic only to healthy instances.
It can also do load balancing, right?
So, you have multiple instances, you can
balance the load across all of these
instances. So, now, back to the question
about network latency,
there are two kinds of load balancers.
There's like application load balancer
and network load balancer.
And the application load balancers are
kind of like layer seven load balancers,
so they kind of terminate the whole HTTP
connection,
then start a new connection to the back
end basically.
Now, if you had that versus a network
load balancer where it only terminates,
let's say, your TCP session,
right? So, the TCP session is terminated
on the load balancer,
but not the TLS, right?
And the TLS, everything happens, let's
say, with the back end. Then, what
happens is you have lower latencies in
the handling, right? So, there might be
some choices in terms of which product
you use that can affect the latency of
your end-to-end traffic, right?
But, in general, I would say that you
wouldn't have to worry about some of
these latencies and stuff like that
until you really hit some high limits.
Right? So, for example, again, going
back to the example of a load balancer,
maybe there is a max bandwidth limit on
the load balancer, which may be very
big, right? Like So, if you're a very
small application, you don't care
usually. But, maybe if you're a very
popular application, then yes, you are
starting to hit towards come closer to
those limits, and then you want to add
maybe more load balancers and things
like that. So, you want to do some kind
of horizontal scaling
and figure out how to balance across
those load balancers. Right? So, I think
that's kind of like the next level of
things that you want to start thinking
about.
The bigger thing I kind of worry about
is cost. Right? So, what's the price of
what I'm using?
So, for example, the load balancer may
have like connections per second, how
many active connections I have, how much
data I'm sending per hour.
And maybe there are two different
products, and one product is slightly
cheaper. So, you may want to use that,
and that's what, you know, you scale up,
right? With the cheaper product,
basically. Maybe that's what you want to
do.
There are other interesting things
where, you know, there are cost
implications. For instance, internet
gateways, if you're sending a lot of
traffic out of the public cloud, there
are some cost implications to that.
So, when you're designing your
application, you want to just make sure
that you're kind of accounting for some
of those aspects.
So, back to your original question about
network latency and VPC configuration,
it's
usually not the public cloud service
that is responsible for your latency,
but it is most likely your design or how
you're using those services that is
causing you the trouble, basically.
And there will always be some option
that you can choose and pick that can
help you avoid some of those latency
problems and things like that.
So, I want to spend the last few minutes
on just seeing if there's key aspects to
comparing and contrasting the VPC
offerings by the major cloud providers.
If there's something specific comes to
your mind between
Amazon VPC or Google private cloud or
Azure or OCI network
or even IBM, if you can comment.
Okay. So, I haven't looked through every
public cloud to see all their feature
sets. What I could compare between is
maybe AWS and OCI because these are
things I've actively used as part of my
work.
I think the key difference that you'll
find between these cloud providers is
the terminology. Like that's the key
difference in my mind because
usually the same product exists in both
the clouds. But they may have different
names. All right? So, for example,
something that's called VPC in AWS, it's
VPC. Right? And that's exactly why we
started this talk because AWS is so big,
everybody is using VPC, but it's not
called VPC in OCI. Right? It's called
VCN, virtual cloud network. But it's the
same thing. Right?
Same thing about There's something
called virtual private gateways. Right?
So, in case of AWS, it's called a
virtual private gateway, but in OCI, it
will be called a dynamic routing
gateway. So, getting around that
terminology could be a little
challenging initially, but you just have
to look for some of the keywords that
you You know, what are you looking for
basically, right? In from your
application point of view. And then, if
you find it, you'll be able to quickly
find it.
The other big difference is like the
default limits. Right? So, for example,
I start on AWS,
my account would have a limit of five
VPCs per region.
If I start on OCI, it's 50 VPCs. Right?
So, those things could be different.
Like I'm sure the numbers are quite
different in Azure, GCP, things like
that.
Same thing like for subnets, maybe AWS
has 200 subnets per VPC.
OCI has 300 subnets per VPC, right? So,
there could be limits differences.
Finally, there could be differences in
the features, right? And I think we
talked about this at the start like what
are the cider blocks that you can use in
your VPC?
In case of AWS, it ranges from /16 to
/28.
In OCI, the ranges could be from /16 to
/30. Okay?
One key difference which I have found,
which was very confusing for me
initially, was that AWS does not have
any regional subnets.
Right?
So, when you create a subnet, it's
actually availability zone specific
subnet only, right? But OCI, and in
fact, I think I recently looked at Azure
as well, and I think they have this
concept of regional subnet. So, you
create one subnet, applies to the
complete region, right?
You know, some features like ACLs, OCI
has support for ACLs which are both
stateful and stateless in the sense
that, you know, you write an ACL in one
direction, the reverse traffic
corresponding to that same flow is
automatically allowed, right? So, that
would be a stateful
ACL entry. On the other hand, like if
you look at AWS, so AWS allows third
party for private link, right? OCI does
not.
In terms of the IPAM tool, the AWS has a
very well developed IPAM tool, which
allows you to monitor IP address and
usage and things like that.
OCI does not have that well developed
tool. And again, I want to point out
that any differences that I'm talking
about today may not be differences 1
month from now if there's a new feature
that's released released by the cloud
operator, right? So, that can always
happen. So, this is just a, you know, at
this point in time analysis of some of
these feature differences.
But yeah, so terminology, limits, and
features, I think those are the three
key things that I would say are the big
differences between these cloud vendors.
Thank you, Nikel. So,
we've covered several topics and of
course this is a pretty vast subject.
But, is there any key topic you think we
missed that you would like to talk
about?
No, I think we went through the whole
gamut of things here. I'm sure I we have
missed something, right? But, this is I
think this is the best we have done and
we have tried to give people kind of an
overview.
So, now you know, hopefully it gives a
jump-start for folks who are kind of
trying to dig in deeper, right? At least
this say, "Oh, I understand at high
level what this looks like. Now, let's
actually go into the documentation and
figure out what each of these things
actually does, right? So, so yeah, in
terms of topics I don't think we have
anything else left to discuss, but this
is all a surface kind of analysis of all
the different features that these cloud
operators provide. So,
it requires another level of analysis.
What is the best way if somebody wanted
to contact you?
It's NikelVGS
on all social media.
You know, I prefer LinkedIn or Twitter,
actually not Twitter X. That's a new
term, so yeah, LinkedIn or X. It's
NikelVGS and you can connect with me
there.
Thank you so much, Nikel. This was a
great discussion. I hope our listeners
learn and like you said, use it as a
jump-start. Thanks again.
Yeah, thank you so much. Bye.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.